<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Ing | Wow this blog looks fancy]]></title>
  <link href="http://lee-jason.github.io/blog/categories/ing/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://lee-jason.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-10-13T10:56:15-07:00</updated>
  <id>http://lee-jason.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jason Lee]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[lee.jason930@gmail.com]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Blog Inauguration]]></title>
    <link href="http://lee-jason.github.io/blog/2014/10/10/blog-inauguration/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-10T16:06:12-07:00</updated>
    <id>http://lee-jason.github.io/blog/2014/10/10/blog-inauguration</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Hi, my name&#8217;s Jason and all these other programming blogs told me that I should start writing.  I&#8217;ve been reading alot about how programmers that write assist in the thinking and solidifying process. It allows you to process what you&#8217;ve just learned and requires you to actually regurgitate it into words that are actually comprehensible. This process will increase understanding by exploring holes of unknown as I reason through it. This is my attempt at being a better person and hopefully a chance to help someone.</p>


<!--more-->


<p>In reality I just wanted a outlet to explode my jumbled self-justified &#8216;brilliant&#8217; thoughts that I probably have already been discussed to death but I just discovered for the first time.  I guess everyone has to start somewhere and this is where I&#8217;m starting.</p>


<p>A little about me. I&#8217;m a programmer who graduated from the University of California Irvine with majors in Information and Computer Science and Music. I enjoy playing the guitar although I don&#8217;t think I&#8217;m getting any better anytime soon. I used a lot of Java in school to learn the theory of CS graduated and decided to pursue the web as a platform of expression. I ended up at my first real job at where they provided web software as a subscription service using a Microsoft web stack. The position was for front-end development which at the time I did not appreciate but I was glad that I had an opportunity to prove myself. </p>


<p>As of this post I&#8217;m currently unemployed. While I did quickly get moved from a junior position to the standard developer role, and won multiple internal awards and nominations for my consistency in delivering. I decided that I would grow faster as a person if I were to reinvest my daily eight hours into myself rather than the company. I do not want to go too into the reasons for departure but the roles and projects that I was assigned to involved mostly overhead management, scheduling, and very little development.  I understand that every programming position in every company needs to deal with bureaucracy, overhead, schedules, and meetings.  I don&#8217;t mind that I really don&#8217;t!  Casual distractions don&#8217;t really bother me.  Its just that when you finally get to the programming and it just involves changing the text value from a line of html, then I get no satisfaction from my job. I appreciate all the mentors that I had for the three years that I&#8217;ve been there and I will take all their advice and teachings to my next career.</p>


<p>So that&#8217;s where I am now.  I have a mess of newly found front-end knowledge, re-brushing up on my backend work with node.js, and some patience to not rush into a new position that I won&#8217;t thoroughly enjoy.  I hope I can truly fulfill the saying &#8216;If you truly love your job then you&#8217;ll never work another day in your life&#8217; or something like that.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
